And I'm delighted to welcome you back to LM engineering on the day that we turn to vectors.
LM 엔지니어링으로 다시 오신 걸 환영합니다 벡터와 만나는 날이죠
Finally, I've been talking about vectors for so long.
벡터 얘기를 너무 오래 했네요
Today we actually get to play with them.
오늘은 실제로 갖고 놀 거예요 get it get it
We are going to be going into Jupyter Lab soon and creating chunks of.
곧 주피터 연구소에 가서 그 덩어리를 만들 거예요
We're creating vectors from chunks of text using OpenAI embeddings, the encoding model that I talked
오픈AI 엠베딩을 이용해 텍스트 덩어리로부터 벡터를 생성합니다 앞서 말씀드린 인코딩
about before.
모델이죠
We're going to store those vectors in the very popular open source vector database called chroma.
유명한 오픈 소스 벡터 데이터베이스에 벡터들을 저장할 겁니다 크로마라고 하죠
And we're then going to visualize the vectors get a sense for what they represent.
그런 다음 벡터들이 뭘 나타내는지를 시각화하는 거죠 get it
And that will then be an exercise for you to keep playing with vectors.
벡터를 계속 갖고 노는 연습이 될 거예요
Try putting your own things into vectors and get a better and better sense of what it what it means
벡터에 여러분만의 것을 입력해 보세요 텍스트를 숫자로 바꾸어 의미를 갖는다는 게 어떤
to have a meaning by turning text into a bunch of numbers.
것인지 더 나은 감각을 갖게 될 거예요 Get it
So let me talk for a moment about these different types of of model.
잠시 이런 다양한 모델 유형에 관해 얘기할게요
How how do you turn text into vectors.
텍스트를 벡터로 바꾸는 방법이요
So there's first of all, there's this very simplistic way that you could do it.
우선 아주 간단한 방법이 있어요
You could for example, say come up with a vocabulary.
예를 들어 어휘를 생각해 보라고 하는 거죠
So come up with a list of possible words.
가능한 단어를 하나씩 생각해 봐요
Let's say the first word in your vocabulary is the word dog, and the second word in your vocabulary
여러분이 아는 단어 중 첫 번째가 개고 두 번째가
is the word cat.
고양이예요
And what you could do is take a block of text and just count the number of times any particular word
텍스트 블록을 하나 골라서 그 안에 있는 특정 단어의 횟수를
is in that block of text.
세는 거예요
And then if the word dog, for example, is in there twice, then you would put a two in the first location
예를 들어 dog라는 단어가 두 번 들어갔다면 첫 번째 장소에 2를
in your vector and cat is in there once.
넣고 캣은 한 번 넣어요
Then you would put one in that location and so on.
그런 다음 해당 위치에 Put을 하는 거죠
So it would really just be counting the number of words of a of a particular type and putting that in
특정 유형의 단어 수를 세서 벡터로 입력하는 거죠
And that would be very simplistic.
아주 단순하죠
It wouldn't reflect the order in which the words are laid out, and it wouldn't reflect the fact, for
단어가 배치된 순서를 반영하지 못해요 같은 단어인 Java가 커피콩이나
example, that the same word Java could refer to a type of coffee bean or to a programming language.
프로그래밍 언어를 참조할 수 없다는 사실도요
It would just be the count of the number of words.
단어 개수만 세면 돼요
So that would be rather simplistic.
그러니 좀 단순하죠
And luckily there are more advanced methods for doing this.
다행히 더 진보된 방법이 있죠
One of the ones that got a lot of attention was in 2013, the arrival of something called word two vec,
주목을 받은 것 중 하나는 2013년에 워드 2벡이라는 것이 등장했을
which was able to use use a deep neural network to start to convert words to vectors in a way that seemed
때입니다 심층 신경망을 이용해 단어를 벡터로 변환할 수 있었죠 그 의미를 반영하는 방식으로요
And it was really it was with word two vec that we started to talk about things like, uh, king minus
우리는 단어 2개를 통해 이런 얘기를 하기 시작했어요 킹에서 남자를 빼면
man plus woman equals queen.
여자가 퀸이 되죠
Uh, Burt is the model that I talked about some time ago.
버트는 제가 전에 말했던 모델이에요
Now it was, uh, it's a transformer model for encoding that Google produced shortly after publishing
이건 변압기 모델로 구글이 논문을 발표한 직후에 만든 부호화 모델입니다 트랜스포머
their paper, Inventing Transformers.
발명이었죠
And the one that we're going to use, OpenAI embeddings, is one that is from OpenAI.
우리가 사용할 OpenAI 엠디딩은 OpenAI에서 온 거예요
And the most recent version is with, uh, updates from 2024.
가장 최근 버전은 2024년의 업데이트예요
Um, and so that is going to be the latest and greatest model that we're going to use for converting
텍스트를 숫자 벡터로 변환하는 데 사용할 수 있는 가장
text into numbers vectors.
최신의 가장 훌륭한 모델이죠
So with that, uh, let me just quickly talk about chroma and then we will get to it.
그럼 이제 채도에 대해 빠르게 이야기해 보고 다시 보도록 하죠. Get in the Cream
So chroma is an example of one of the, uh, vector data stores.
채도는 벡터 데이터 저장소의 한 예인데요
There are quite a few of them, and many of the of the main databases also now support taking vectors
꽤 많이 있고, 메인 데이터베이스도 벡터를 찾고 검색하는
and searching on vectors.
것을 지원하죠
An example MongoDB that lots of people use as a NoSQL data store will also take vectors and can act
많은 사람들이 NoSQL 데이터 스토어로 사용하는 몽고DB의 예는 벡터를 취하고 벡터 데이터베이스로
as a vector database.
작용할 수 있어요
But Cromer was sort of first and foremost a vector database.
크로머는 무엇보다도 벡터 데이터베이스였어요
And this is uh, its website.
이게 그 웹사이트예요
Uh, and you can see it makes a, it's got better pictures than I had with an old school, uh, Mac
보시다시피 옛날 맥 인터페이스보다 사진이 더 잘 나와요
Uh, but the idea that, that you could do a query in your I application and it can retrieve from a
I 응용 프로그램에서 쿼리를 할 수 있고 여러 벡터에서 데이터를 검색할
bunch of vectors and that retrieve data gets put into the prompt and query.
수 있고 그 데이터를 입력한 프롬프트와 큐리에 넣는 거죠.
So it's a fancier version of the diagram that I showed you last time.
저번에 보여드린 다이어그램의 좀 더 화려한 버전이에요
Uh, so this is Cromer.
이쪽은 크로머예요
This is what we'll be using to store our vectors.
벡터를 저장하기 위해 사용할 것들이죠
And I think quite enough chit chat.
잡담은 충분히 한 것 같네요
It's time for us to get JupyterLab, and it's time for us to use vectors first hand.
JupyterLab을 get 할 때입니다 벡터를 먼저 사용할 때죠
See you there.
거기서 봐요